Guide to the Boris Moiseevich Sapir Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series XIV: Papers of F. (Fedor) (1871-1947) and Lidiia Dan
  - Subseries XIV.3: Arranged Manuscripts
    - Dan, Lidiia Diary excerpts --Memoirs; --"Neozhidannyi vizit:Bukharin u Dana"; --Notes on F. (Fedor) Dan's letters to Berta Borisovna Mering; --On Vera Figner; --On Val'ter Krivitskii; --"Zapisi" - (2 binders) (Box 57 54)
    - Kliachko, S.L. (Box 57 54)
    - Miscellaneous and undentified notes (Box 57 54)
    - Dan, Lidiia Diaries, 1942-1944; 1944-1947; 1947; 1947 & 1948; 1949-1951; 1955-1958; 1959-1962 (Box 55)
    - "Novyi Put'" files, (8 folders ) (Box 56)
  - Subseries XIV.4: Subject Files
    - Compensation for losses by Dans in World War II (Box 57)
    - Death of F. (Fedor) Dan (Box 57)
    - Death of Lidiia Dan (Box 57)
    - Lectures by F. (Fedor) Dan, 1940s (Box 57)
    - Malinovskii, Roman (Box 57)
    - Martov, L. (1873-1923) (Box 57)
  - Subseries XIV.5: Publications of Menshevism History Project
    - Aronson, Gregor K istorii pravogo Techeniia Sredi men'shevikov (Box 58)
    - Revoliutsionnaia iunost' vospominaniia (Box 58)
    - Nicolaevsky, Boris I. Men'sheviki v dni oktiabr'skogo perevorota (Box 58)
    - Miscellaneous clippings and publications (Box 58)
- Series XV: Papers of Petr A. (Petr Abramovich) and Sofiia Garvi
  - Subseries XV.1: Arranged Correspondence
    - Aronson, Gregor (1887-1968) (Box 59)
    - Garvi, Petr A. (Petr Abramovich) (1881-1944) With various people (Box 59)
    - Garvi, Sofiia With various people (Box 59)
    - Sapir, Boris (Box 59)
  - Subseries XV.2: Arranged Manuscripts
    - Petr A. (Petr Abramovich) Garvi "Rabochaia kooperatsiia (1917-1921)" (Box 60)
    - "Vospominaniia ... ch. 2-a", (1906-16) (Box 60)
    - "Vospominaniia ... Peterburg 1906 g. ... tetrad' II", ( (2 folders) ) (Box 60)
    - "Vospominaniia ... 1907 g.;" "1917 god" (Box 60)
    - "Vospominaniia ... posle 3-go iiunia 1907 g." (Box 60)
    - "Vospominaniia ... 1912 g.", (2 folders ) (Box 60)
    - "Vospominaniia sotsialdemokrata", 1899-1904 & 1905, (2 volumes bound ms.) (Box 61)
    - Essays in German (Box 61)
    - Notes & drafts, (2 folders ) (Box 61)
- Series XVI: Papers of Boris L'vovich Gurevich [Dvinov]
  - Subseries XVI.1: Cataloged correspondence
    - Dan, F. (Fedor) (1871-1947) To Boris L'vovich and Sofiia Gurevich, [v.p.], [n.d.] & 1926-1942, (2 a.l.s., 14 a.p.c.s.) (Box 62)
  - Subseries XVI.2: Arranged correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (Box 62)
    - Abramovitch, Raphael A. (Box 62)
    - Dan, Lidiia, (2 folders ) (Box 62)
    - Garvi, Sofiia (Box 62)
  - Subseries XVI.3: Arranged Manuscripts
    - Fainsod, Merle "Controls and Tensions in the Soviet System" (Box 62)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 62)
    - Subject files: Bratstvo russkoi pravdy & L.N. Nol'de (Box 62)
    - Nikolai Evgenyev'ich Khokhlov case (Box 62)
    - Nationality question (Box 62)
    - Natsional'no-Trudovoi Soiuz, (2 folders ) (Box 63)
    - Nazi documents, ( copies (folders1-2)) (Box 63)
    - Nazi documents, ( copies (folders 3-4)) (Box 64)
    - Rightist Russian emigre groups (miscellaneous groups) (Box 64)
    - Soiuz bor'by za osvobozhdenie narodov Rossii (SBONR) (Box 64)
    - "Trest" & "Vnutrenniaia liniia" (Box 64)
    - Alexander Trushnovich case (Box 64)
    - Vlasov movment (Box 64)
    - Clippings, miscellaneous (Box 64)
- Series XVII: Papers of Abram Lazarevich Vigderzon
  - Arranged Correspondence with Boris Sapir, (4 folders) (Box 65)
  - Notebooks (Box 65)
  - "Sionisty na Solovkakh ... 1925 g." (Box 65)
  - "Dokumenty, zametki, stat'i, 1916-80 (k istorii odnoi sem'i)" (Box 65)
- Series XVIII: Papers of Zagranichnaia Delegatsiia RSDRP
  - Subseries XVIII.1: Cataloged Correspondence
    - Dan, F. (Fedor) (1871-1947) To Boris Sapir, Berlin, [n.d.] & 1929-1932, (4 a.l.s., with envelope) (Box 66)
  - Subseries XVIII.2: Arranged Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1920s (Box 66)
    - Letters from Soviet Russia, 1920s, (3 folders) (Box 66)
    - Letters from exiled Social Democrats, 1920s (Box 66)
    - "Evsei" (Box 66)
    - Iakubson, Izrail' Solomonovich (Box 66)
    - Iakubson, Lev Solomonovich (Box 66)
    - Kogan, Lidiia Evseevna (Box 66)
    - Paletika, Elena Konstantinovna (Box 66)
    - Rashkovskii, Ivan Grigor'evich (Box 66)
  - Subseries XVIII.3: Arranged Manuscripts
    - Transcript of minutes - "K zasedaniiu zagr. deleg. 21.5.30 g. ", (4 folders) (Box 66)
    - Notebooks of minutes "Protokoly ZDRSDRP" with related notes, documents, and correspondence, 1922-29; 1929-31; 1931-35; 1936-37; 1940-43; 1943-47; 1947-49; 1949-51 (Box 67)
    - Boris Sapir Notebooks, 1920s-30s, (17 items) (Box 67)
    - Subject files:Berlinskii klub im. Martova, 1931-1932, (4 folders) (Box 68)
    - Petr A. (Petr Abramovich) Garvi's report on party conference on socialism & war, 1935 (Box 68)
    - "K raskolu ZD", 1954-57 (Box 68)
    - "New York group", 1941-471948-53 (Box 68)
    - "New York group" (materials kept by Leo Lande) (Box 68)
    - Sapir Notebooks, 1920s-30s (Box 69)
    - Socialist Youth International, [n.d.] 1920s-30s; 1924-25; 1926; 1927; 1928; 1929; 1930; 1931; 1932p; 1934; 1935; 1936; 1937; 1938 (Box 69)
    - "Sotsialisticheskii Vestnik" mailing list, 1958 (Box 69)
    - Miscellaneous notes and clippings (Box 69)
- Series XIX: Papers of Leon Shapiro
  [gift of Mrs. Leon Shapiro, 1985]
  - Subseries XIX.1: Cataloged Correspondence
    - Sapir, Boris To Leon Shapiro, [Blaricum, Netherlands], 1967-1984, (30 autograph letters signed (with 1 envelope), 183 t.l.s.(with 9 envelopes), 9 a.p.c.s., 3 t.p.c.s.) (Box 70)
- Series XX: Oversize
  - Subseries XX.1: Printed Materials
    - Bich: Satiriko iumoristicheskii ezhenendel'nik, Petrograd: 16, Aprelia1917 g (Box 71)
  - Subseries XX.2: Photocopies of Russian Newspapers
    - Den', 1917 (Box 71)
    - Edinstvo; Nashe edinstvo, 1917-1918 (Box 71)
    - Iskra, 1917-1918 (Box 71)
    - Luch; Novyi Luch, 1917 (Box 71)
    - Rabochaia Mysl', 1898-1902 (Box 71)
    - Vpered, 1917 (Box 71)